Finding Aid for University of Michigan. Office of the Registrar Records 1840-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office of the Registrar (University of Michigan), records 1840-2003, 1867-1993
University of Michigan. Office of the Registrar.
24 oversize volumes
24.5 linear feet
Admission records, statistics on faculty and students, and records of examinations; also reports, petitions, and resolutions of the faculty of the University's College of Literature, Science and the Arts.
87304 BImu Bimu B5 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (Donor No. 100 ) has come to the library in periodic accessions since the 1930s.
The Office of the Registrar records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Office of the Registrar record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Student Academic Records -- Box 25 (removed to vault)
In 1846, the faculty authorized the position of secretary of the faculty of the Department of Literature, Science and the Arts. The secretary was to create a permanent written record of faculty proceedings and to keep student records. The earliest use of the word "registrar" in a title occurred in 1863 when student record keeping was separated from the secretary's position. Edward P. Evans, professor of modern languages, was the first to be elected to this one-year position. According to The University of Michigan Encyclopedic Survey edited by Wilfred Shaw (Ann Arbor: University Press, 1942), student discipline problems caused the registrar's position to be abolished between 1872 and 1888. During this time the secretary of the faculty resumed the duties of the registrar.
In 1875, Paul R. B. de Pont, instructor in French, was elected secretary of the faculty. He served as secretary until 1888 when the regents appointed him registrar of the Department of Literature, Science and the Arts.
In 1878/79, a four-year program called the "English Course" was added to the curriculum. It was at this time that the credit system was substituted for a set schedule of four prescribed years of study. Additionally, the number of required courses in the programs were reduced to allow for electives.
In 1882, the "University System" was introduced as an option in the Department of Literature, Science and the Arts. The University System did not require a student to complete a fixed number of required courses, but rather, allowed the student, under the direction of a faculty committee, to focus his studies. Upon the completion of four years and a satisfactory written examination, a bachelor of arts degree was conferred. "A master of arts degree was granted to the writer of a brilliant examination and a meritorious thesis." (The University of Michigan Encyclopedic Survey) The University System program led to both undergraduate and higher degrees; there was not yet a separate graduate school. Consequently, the University System and the work for advanced degrees became inextricably bound together. Records of the students of the University System were kept by faculty committees, separate from "regular" students.
The Board of Regents authorized a plan in 1871 to admit graduates of accredited high schools by diploma. Michigan high schools were visited by a university faculty committee that appraised the schools for their work in science, philosophy, and the arts. A school had to pass the university's criteria in all three of the above areas to become accredited. Accreditation specifications were changed in 1876 to accommodate schools strong in only one or two of the subject areas. This new partial accreditation system allowed students entrance to select university programs depending on the accreditation status of the secondary school from where they graduated. The Department of Literature, Science and the Arts maintained four separate sets of entrance requirements throughout the 1890s. Admission by diploma was extended to high schools outside of Michigan in 1884. In May of 1900, a single system of entrance requirements went into effect. School visits were taken over by the Bureau of Co-operation with Educational Institutions in 1932.
Incoming students in the Department of Literature, Science and the Arts took their credentials directly to the dean, rather than the president, as of the 1895/96 school year. Checking of admission credits was a task divided between the dean and the registrar, with the registrar administering the admissions of freshmen who had the customary preparation, and those with a very small amount of advanced credit or with extra high school credit. Besides reviewing freshman admissions, the registrar's responsibilities included interviewing students and acting as an intermediary between students and faculty in all matters involving study loads and student records.
Registration for the professional academic units of pharmacy, engineering, and the School of Graduate Studies was originally under literary faculty control. The pharmacy admission records were under the auspices of the Department of Literature, Science and the Arts registrar until approximately 1875, the Department of Engineering until 1903, and the School of Graduate Studies until 1912.
In 1907, at the time of the appointment of Dean John O. Reed, administrative work by the president was almost entirely relinquished. Administrative affairs of the Department of Literature, Science and the Arts were put into the hands of its own officers, the dean, and the registrar. A new title, University Registrar, was created in July 1915. It was at this time that the Office of the Registrar became an office of the university's central administration, completely independent of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts. (It was also in 1915 that the Department of Literature, Science and the Arts was renamed College of Literature, Science and the Arts.) In May 1925, regental by-laws made the Office of the Registrar directly responsible to the regents through the president. The office became more specialized in 1929 with the creation of four divisions: Admissions, Records, Statistics, and Editorial. In 1949 the Office of the Director of Admissions, a separate administrative unit, was created due to the increase in the number of admissions after World
War II. In 1954 the name of the Office of the Registrar was changed to the Office of Registration and Records. At the same time, the responsibility of orientation of new students was added to this office. The Time Schedule (course catalog) responsibilities were added to the office during the 1963/64 academic school year. Orientation and Scheduling were made independent units in 1967.
During the winter term of 1972, the concept of Computer Registration Involving Student Participation (CRISP) grew out of a class project in a computer class taught by Professor Bernard E. Galler. CRISP was instituted in 1975 as an on-line registration program.
Touch-tone CRISP was first introduced in November 1994. Beginning in March 1995, it was the mandatory form of registration for most students. In addition to helping students with registration needs, other CRISP services include transcripts requests, certification for loans and placement, academic record information, class schedules, term grade reports, and student directory changes.
Wolverine Access, developed by the registrar's office in the summer of 1994, is an on-line service that enables students to access current student data. Students can access their own grades, class schedule, and academic report. They can also check on availability of classes and look at their account statement. This service was first made available through a client server with Macintosh machines at campus computing sites. Wolverine Access is now available on the World Wide Web.
First Registrars
1843-1846 Unofficial secretary to faculty of LS&A
1846-1863 Secretary to faculty of LS&A
Registrar of faculty of LS&A - 1863-1872
1863/64 Edward P. Evans
1864/65-1866/67 Edward Olney
1867/68 Stillman Williams Robinson
1870/71 Albert Henderson Pattengill
1871/72 Edward Lorraine Walter
1871/72 Jules Frederick Billard
Registrar of LS&A
1888-1906 Paul R. B. dePont
Registrar of LS&A and Secretary of Administrative Board
1906-1908 John William Bradshaw
Registrar of LS&A and Editor of University Publications
1908-1915 Arthur Graham Hall
Registrar
1925-1954 Ira Melville Smith
Registrar of the University
1954-1964 Edward G. Groesbeck
Registrar
1967-1985 Harris D. Olson (Associate Registrar)
1967-1985 Douglas Wooley (Associate Registrar)
1985-1991 A.A. Stuart
1992-1993 Douglas Wooley (interim)
1993-1996 Laura McCain Patterson
1996-2001 Thomas McElvain
2001- Paul Robinson
The records of the Registrar document the functions of the registration and admission of students at the University of Michigan including on admission and registration policy and procedures, official lists of registrants, and the automation of registration process. The records are organized in seven series: Admissions; Faculty Reports, Petitions and Resolutions; Topical Files, Faculty Card Files, and Academic Record Project.
Subjects:
College registrars--Michigan.; Education--Evaluation.; Education, Higher--Michigan.; Student registration.; Universities and colleges--Admission.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--Admission.; University of Michigan. College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.; University of Michigan--Examinations.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Office of the Registrar.
- Admissions
  The Admissions series (8 linear feet) consists of admission records and applications for advanced standing. An admission form was generated for each student that applied to the university. The forms most relevant for genealogical research are those dated 1856-1871, as they include parent's name, home address and occasionally the age of the student. The application for advanced standing indicates the institutions previously attended by the student. The researcher should note that there are related outsize volumes described at the end of the finding aid.
  - Admission Records
    - 1856, 1861-1879, 19 folders (Box 1)
    - 1880-1889, 13 folders (Box 2)
    - 1890-1898, 9 volumes (Box 3)
    - 1899-1907, 10 volumes (Box 4)
    - 1889-1897 (Volume 1)
    - 1897-1905 (Volume 2)
    - 1905-1913 (Volume 3)
  - Admission Register
    - 1861-1872 (Box 14)
    - 1872-1890 (Box 14)
  - Applications for Advanced Standing
    - 1889-1899, 11 volumes (Box 5)
    - 1900-1920 (Box 6)
  - Admission on Advanced Standing Register 1896-1900 (Box 14)
  - Registration Records
    - Dentistry
      - 1875-1903 (Volume 4)
      - 1903-1908 (Volume 5)
    - Engineering 1895-1908 (Volume 6)
    - Homeopathic Medicine
      - 1875-1903 (Volume 7)
      - 1903-1908 (Volume 8)
    - Law
      - 1864-1871 (Volume 9)
      - 1872-1892 (Volume 10)
      - 1892-1905 (Volume 11)
      - 1905-1908 (Volume 12)
    - Literary
      - 1864-1871 (Volume 13)
      - 1872-1888 (Volume 14)
      - 1888-1894 (Volume 15)
      - 1895-1902 (Volume 16)
      - 1903-1908 (Volume 17)
    - Medicine
      - 1864-1872 (Volume 18)
      - 1872-1892 (Volume 19)
      - 1892-1908 (Volume 20)
    - Pharmacy
      - 1878-1892 (Volume 21)
      - 1893-1908 (Volume 22)
    - Summer Session 1894-1896 (Volume 23)
  - Examination Records 1852-1860 (Volume 24)
- Faculty Reports, Petitions, and Resolutions
  The Faculty Reports, Petitions and Resolutions series (5.5 linear feet) documents the work and decision making powers of the Faculty of the Department of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A) as they acted on student petitions, academic standing, and other matters relating to admissions. This series contains a wealth of information relating to high school accreditation and its relationship to UM admissions. The records were originally bundled in envelopes by academic year, with a contents listing of items on the outside of each envelope. This list of items has been retained and placed in the appropriate folder for easier access to the contents. The records for any academic year are divided into four folders: General, Candidates for Degrees, Committee on Substitutions, and School Visits.
  The General category contains petitions, curricula changes, and issues that were voted on by the faculty. The Candidates for Degrees records are comprised of one-page documents outlining the academic history of the student as well as any future academic plans. The Committee on Substitutions records consist of letters written by students asking for substitutions of required courses. Of particular interest are the School Visits records documenting accreditation of secondary schools. The school visit reports include a listing of teachers and the subject they taught, as well as an evaluation of their performance. Also included in the report is the student population size, number of books in the library, and areas within the school needing improvement. Further information on these visits are located in the "University of Michigan. Bureau of School Services" record group.
  - 1878/79
    - General (Box 7)
    - Resolutions and Committee Reports (Box 7)
  - 1879/80
    - Resolutions and Committee Reports (Box 7)
  - 1880/81
    - Reports of Committees and Resolutions, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1881/82
    - Reports of Committees and Resolutions, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Orchard Lake Academy (Michigan Military Academy) (Box 7)
  - 1882/83
    - General (Box 7)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 7)
    - School Visits (Box 7)
    - Textbooks (used for various courses) (Box 7)
  - 1883/84
    - General (Box 7)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 7)
    - Student Petitions (Box 7)
    - School Visits (Box 7)
  - 1884/85
    - General, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 7)
    - Committee on Substitutions (Box 7)
    - School Visits (Box 7)
  - 1885/86
    - General, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 7)
    - Committee on Substitutions (Box 7)
    - School Visits (Box 7)
  - 1886/87
    - General (Box 7)
    - Standing Committee (Box 7)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 7)
    - School Visits (Box 7)
  - 1887/88
    - General (Box 7)
    - Standing Committee (Box 7)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 7)
    - School Visits (Box 7)
  - 1888/89
    - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Committee on Substitutions (Box 8)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 8)
    - School Visits (Box 8)
  - 1889/90
    - General (Box 8)
    - Committee on Substitutions (Box 8)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 8)
    - School Visits, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - 1890/91
    - General (Box 8)
    - Committee on Substitutions (Box 8)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 8)
    - School Visits, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1891/92
    - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 8)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 8)
    - University System-Higher Degrees (Box 8)
    - School Visits, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1892/93
    - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 8)
    - Committee on Substitutions, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 8)
    - School Visits, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - 1893/94
    - General (Box 9)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 9)
    - Committee on Substitutions (Box 9)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 9)
    - School Visits, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Answers to Requests and Petitions (Box 9)
  - 1894/95
    - General, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 9)
    - Committee on Substitutions, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 9)
    - School Visits, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Answers to Requests and Petitions (Box 9)
  - 1895/96
    - General (Box 9)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 9)
    - Committee on Substitutions, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Report of Committees (Box 9)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 9)
    - School Visits, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - 1896/97
    - General (Box 10)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 10)
    - Committee on Substitutions, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Report of Committees (Box 10)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 10)
    - School Visits, 4 folders (Box 10)
  - 1897/98
    - General (Box 10)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 10)
    - Committee on Substitutions, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Report of Committees (Box 10)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 10)
    - School Visits, 4 folders (Box 10)
  - 1898/99
    - General (Box 10)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 10)
    - Committee on Substitutions, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 10)
    - School Visits, 4 folders (Box 10)
  - 1899/00
    - General (Box 10)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 10)
    - Committee on Substitutions, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Literary/Law Committee (Box 10)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 10)
    - School Visits, 5 folders (Box 10)
  - 1900/01
    - General (Box 11)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 11)
    - Committee on Substitutions (Box 11)
    - Report of Committees (Box 11)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 11)
    - School Visits, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - 1901/02
    - General (Box 11)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 11)
    - Committee on Hours (Box 11)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 11)
    - School Visits, 5 folders (Box 11)
  - 1902/03
    - General (Box 11)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 11)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 11)
    - School Visits, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - 1903/04
    - General (Box 11)
    - Committee on Advanced Credits (Box 11)
    - Committee on Hours (Box 11)
    - Candidates for Degrees (Box 11)
    - School Visits (2 Folders) (Box 11)
- Topical Files 1840-1957
  The Topical Files series (2.5 linear feet) includes statistics compiled by the Office of the Registrar and information documenting students in the University System. Statistics include lists of delinquent students, hometowns, and scholarship charts. The University System records consist of applications for higher degrees, committee reports, and a listing of thesis subjects. The researcher should note that there are related outsize volumes described at the end of the finding aid.
  - General 1900-1933 (Box 11)
  - American Association of Collegiate Registrars
    - 1920 (Box 11)
    - 1921-22 (Box 11)
  - Applications for Higher Degrees 1891/92 (Box 11)
  - Board of Regents (correspondence) 1908-1919 (Box 11)
  - Candidates for Degrees 1906 (Box 11)
  - Deficiencies, Record of 1876-1891 (Box 14)
  - Delinquent Lists
    - 1910-1913 (Box 11)
    - 1917-1924 (Box 11)
  - Delinquents, Register of 1893-1896 (Box 14)
  - Examinations, Record of 1867-1874 (Box 14)
  - Faculty Statistics 1900-1957 (Box 11)
  - Fraternity and Sorority Scholarship Record 1912-1924 (Box 11)
  - Hometown Lists
    - 1916-1920 (Box 12)
    - 1922-1924 (Box 12)
  - Honors Convocation
    - 1924 (Box 12)
    - 1925 (Box 12)
  - Military Credit 1920/21 (Box 12)
  - Occupation of Parents 1911/12 (report on) (Box 12)
  - Renumbering of Courses 1923 (Box 12)
  - Report
    - Report on Methods of Increasing the Intellectual Interest of Students at the University of Michigan, 1924 (Box 12)
  - Scholarship Charts 1929-1938 (incomplete) (Box 12)
  - Statistics
    - Miscellaneous 1910-1924, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Registration Statistics
      - 1840-1896 (Box 12)
      - 1916-1919 (Box 12)
      - 1920 (Box 12)
      - 1921 (Box 12)
      - 1922 (Box 12)
      - 1923 (Box 12)
    - Statistics of Daily Registration: Old to Modern 1904-1924 (Box 14)
    - Student Records 1860-1860 (Box 14)
      (of individual courses)
  - Student Rosters
    - 1920/21 (Box 12)
    - 1921/22, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - 1922/23, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - University System
    - Applications for Higher Degree
      - 1885/86 (Box 12)
      - 1886/87 (Box 12)
      - 1887/88 (Box 12)
      - 1888/89 (Box 12)
      - 1889/90 (Box 12)
    - Committee Reports
      - 1883/84 (Box 12)
      - 1884/85 (Box 12)
      - 1885/86 (Box 12)
      - 1886/87 (Box 12)
      - 1887/88 (Box 12)
      - 1889/90 (Box 12)
      - 1890/91 (Box 12)
    - Thesis Subjects
      - 1886/87 (Box 12)
      - 1889/90 (Box 12)
    - Statistical Information (outsize box)
      - Geographic Hometown Location 1915-1922 (Box 13)
      - Fall Class Student Lists 1876-1879 (Box 13)
      - High Schools (accredited, admitted from) 1871-1878 (Box 13)
- Faculty Card Files 1926-1942
  The Faculty Card Files series (1.5 linear feet) is comprised of an alphabetical run of 3" x 5" cards. Each card represents a faculty member, with information on academic education, courses taught, sabbaticals, and retirement date. It is unclear when the cards were first created, perhaps around 1930, however there are entries dating back to 1926. It appears that no cards were created after 1942.
  - A-MI (Box 15)
  - Mo-Z (Box 16)
- Topical Files 1924-1994
  The Topical Files, 1924-1994 series (3 linear feet) was received as part of the 1994 accession. The bulk of the material, dating from 1959-1993, contains documentation on the registration process when it was facilitated through an IBM mainframe. Additionally, there is information on the Computer Registration Involving Student Participation (CRISP). The files contain information on the registration process, types of forms used, guidelines followed, and reports. There are scattered files from 1924-1958 on topics such as: Analysis of Grade Point Average, Freshman Grade Pint Averages, and Veterans.
  - Academic Data Procedures, Committee for the Study of 1965 (Box 17)
  - Academic Record Analysis 1929, 1937, 1938-1943 (Box 17)
  - Academic Label Program 1967-1974 (Box 17)
  - Academic System Affairs Committee, 1963/4 (Box 17)
  - Address Collection 1973 (Box 17)
  - Admissions 1947 (Box 17)
  - Age Study 1959 (Box 17)
  - Analysis of Grade Distribution 1924/25 (Box 17)
  - Budget/Planning Conference 1991 (Box 17)
  - Computer Registration Involving Student Participation (CRISP)
    - General
      - 1973 (Box 17)
      - 1974, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - 1975/76 (Box 17)
      - 1977 (Box 17)
      - 1981 (Box 17)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 17)
    - CRISP Committee, 1972/3 (Box 17)
    - Draft Reports 1973 (Box 17)
    - Implementation Group 1974/75 (Box 17)
    - Operators' Guides 1975 (Box 17)
    - Questionnaire Results 1976 (Box 17)
  - Costs 1967-1970 (re: data processing) (Box 17)
  - Course Data Bases, University 1977-1984 (Box 17)
  - Data Systems Center 1967-1970 (Box 17)
  - Digitek Forms 1969 (Box 17)
  - Enrollment Count Procedure 1962-1963 (Box 17)
  - Fees 1958-1966 (student) (Box 17)
  - Flow Charts 1958-1968 (Box 17)
  - Forms 1956-1978 (blank) (Box 17)
  - Freshman Grade Point Averages 1926-1958 (Box 17)
  - Grade Procedures 1958-1966 (Box 17)
  - Grades Task Team 1986 (Box 17)
  - Grading System, Report of Conference Committee on 1925-1935 (Box 17)
  - Graduate Hold Procedure 1968-1978 (Box 17)
  - Graduate Program Guidelines 1976-1977 (Box 17)
  - Graduate Records Study 1940 (Box 17)
  - Graduate School
    - IBM Card Codes circa 1959 (Box 17)
    - Reporting Procedures 1947 (Box 17)
    - Graduate School/Registrar Meeting Minutes 1974-1977 (Box 17)
  - Handbooks
    - Information Retrieval Systems Handbook, 1984 (Box 17)
    - Student Database Terminal Handbook, 1973 (Box 17)
    - University Course Data Base Handbook, 1979 (Box 17)
  - Hold Credit Procedure 1959 (Box 17)
  - Housing Reports 1966 (Box 17)
  - Housing Survey 1959 (Box 17)
  - LS&A Policies 1974-1977 (Box 17)
  - LS&A/Registrar Meetings 1973-1977 (Box 17)
  - Michigan Junior College Study 1959 (Box 17)
  - North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools 1927-1937 (Box 17)